[Music]
Reedman
reads The Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
[Music]
16 Jonas did not want to go back.
He didn't want the memories he didn't want the honor, didn't want the wisdom, didn't want the
pain. He wanted his childhood again, his scraped knees in ball games. He sat in
his dwelling alone, watching through the window, seeing children at play, citizens
bicycling home from uneventful days at work, ordinary lives free of anguish
because he had been selected, as others before him had, to bear their burden.
But the choice was not his. He returned each day to the Annex
room. The Giver was gentle with him for many days following the terrible shared memory of
war. "There are so many good memories," The Giver reminded Jonas. And it
was true. By now Jonas had experienced countless bits of happiness, things he had never known of
before he'd seen a birthday party, with one child singled out and celebrated on
his day, so that now he understood the joy of being an individual, special and unique and
proud. He had visited museums and seen paintings filled with all the colors he
could now recognize a name. In one ecstatic memory he had ridden a gleaming brown horse across a
field that smelled of damp grass, and it dismounted beside a small stream from
which both he and and the horse drank cold, clear water. Now he understood about animals;
and in the moment that the horse turned from the stream and nudged Jonas's
shoulder affectionately with its head, he perceived the bonds between animal and
human. He had walked through woods, and sat at night beside a
campfire. Although he had through the memories learned about the pain of loss and
loneliness, now he gained, too and understanding of solitude and its
joy. "What is your favorite?" Jonas asked The Giver. "You don't have to give it away
yet," he added quickly. "Just tell me about it, so I can look forward to it cuz I'll
have to receive it when your job is done." The Giver
smiled. "Lie down," he said. "I'm happy to give it to
you." Jonas felt the joy of it as soon as the memory began sometimes Sometimes it took a
while for him to get his bearings, to find his place. But this time he fit
right in and felt the happiness that pervaded the memory. He was in a room filled with
people, and it was warm, with Fire Light glowing on a
hear He could see through a window that outside it was night, and snowing. There
were colored lights: red and green and yellow, twinkling from a tree which was,
oddly, inside the room. On a table, lighted candles stood in
a polished golden holder and cast a soft, flickering glow. He could smell things
cooking, and he could hear soft laughter. A golden-haired dog lay
sleeping on the floor. On the floor there were packages wrapped in brightly
colored paper and tied with gleaming ribbons. As Jonas watched, a small child
began to pick up the packages and pass them around the room: to other children,
to adults who are obviously parents, and to an older, quiet couple, man and woman,
who sat smiling together on a couch.
While Jonas watched, the people began one by one to untie the ribbons on the
packages, to unwrap the bright papers, open the boxes and revealed toys and clothing and
books. There were cries of delight. They hugged one another. The small child went
and sat on the lap of the old woman, and she rocked Ed him and rubbed her cheek
against
his. Jonas opened his eyes and lay contentedly on the bed, still luxuriating
in the warm and comforting memory. It had all been there, all the things he had
learned to treasure. "What did you perceive?" The Giver asked. "Warmth," Jonas replied, "and
happiness. And— —let me think f Family. That it was a celebration of some sort, a
holiday. And something else— —I can't quite get the word for
it." "It will come to you." "Who were the old people? Why were they there?" It had
puzzled Jonas, seeing them in the room.
The Old of the community did not ever leave their special place, the House of
the Old, where they were so well cared for and respected. "They were called
Grandparents grandparents Grandparents. It meant parents of the
parents long ago." "Back and back and back?"
Jonas began to laugh. "So actually, there could be parents of the parents of the
parents of the parents?" The Giver laughed, too. "That's right. It's a little like
looking at yourself in a mirror looking at yourself looking in a mirror." Jonas
frowned. "But my parents must have had parents! I never thought about it before.
Who are my parents of the parents Where are they?" "You could go look in the Hall
of Open Records. You'd find the names. But think, son. If you apply for
children, then who will be their parents of the parents Who will be their
grandparents?" "My mother and father, of course." "And where will they
be?" Jonas thought. "Oh," he said slowly. "When I finish my training and
become a full adult, I'll be given my own dwelling then when Lily does, a few years
later, she'll get her own dwelling, and maybe a spouse, and children if she
applies for them, and then Mother and Father—" "That's right." "As long as they're
still working and contributing to the community they'll they'll go and live
with the other Childless Adults. And they won't be part of my life
anymore. "And after that, when the time comes, they'll go to the House of the
Old," Jonas went on. He was thinking aloud.
"And they'll be well cared for, and respected, and when they're
released, there will be a celebration."
"Which you won't attend," The Giver pointed out. "No, of course not, because I won't
even know about it. By then I'll be so busy with my own life. And Lily will, too.
So our children, if we have them, won't know who their parents of parents are,
either. "It seems to work pretty well that way, doesn't it? The way we do it in our
community?" Jonas asked. "I just didn't realize there was any other way till I received that
memory." "It works," The Giver agreed. Jonas hesitated. "I certainly liked the memory,
though. I can see why it's your favorite.
I couldn't quite get the word for the whole feeling of it, the feeling that was
so strong in the room." "Love," The Giver told him. Jonas repeated it. "Love." It was a word
and concept new to him.
They were both silent for a minute. Then Jonas said, "Giver?" "Yes?" "I feel very foolish
saying this. Very, very foolish." "No need.
Nothing is foolish here. Trust the memories and how they make you feel." "Well
Jonah said, looking at the floor, "I know you don't have the memory
anymore, because you gave it to me, so maybe you won't understand this—" "I will. I
am left with a vague wisp of that one; and I have many other memories of
families, and holidays, and happiness. Of love." Jonas blurted out what he was
feeling. "I was thinking that well, I can see that it wasn't a very practical way
to live, with the Old right there in the same place, where maybe they wouldn't be
well taken care of, the way they are now, and that we have a better arranged way
of doing things. But anyway I I was thinking, I mean feeling, actually, that it
was kind of nice, then. And that I wish we could be that
way that you could be my grandparent. The family and the memory seemed a little
more—" He faltered, not able to find the word he wanted. "A little more complete," The Giver
suggested. Jonas nodded. "I liked the feeling of love," he
confessed. He glanced nervously at the speaker on the wall, reassuring himself that no one was
listening. "I wish we still had that," he whispered. "Of course," he added quickly, "I
do understand that it wouldn't work very well. And that it's much better to be
organized the way we are now. I can see that it was a dangerous way to live." "What
do you mean?" Jonas hesitated. He wasn't certain, really, what he had meant.
He could feel that there was risk involved, though he wasn't sure how. "Well,"
he said finally, grasping for an explanation, "they had fire right there in
the room. There was a fire burning in the fireplace. And there were candles on a
table and I can certainly see why those things were outlawed. "Still," he said slowly, almost to
himself, "I did like the light they made.
And the warmth."
[Music]
"Father? Mother?" Jonas asked tentatively after the evening
meal. "I have a question I want to ask you." "What is it, Jonas?" his father
asked. He made himself say the words, though he felt flushed with
embarrassment. He had rehearsed them in his mind all the way home from the
Annex. "Do you love me?" There was an awkward silence for a moment and Father gave a little
chuckle. Jonas. You, of all people.
Precision of language, please! "What do you mean?" Jonas asked.
Amusement was not at all what he had anticipated. "Your father means that you
used a very generalized word, so meaningless that it's become almost
obsolete," his mother explained carefully.
Jonas stared at them. Meaningless? He had never before felt anything as meaningful
as the memory. "And of course our community can't function smoothly if
people don't use precise language. You could ask, 'Do you enjoy me?' The answer is
'Yes,'" his mother said. "Or," his father suggested, "'Do you take pride in my
accomplishments the answer is wholeheartedly 'Yes.'" "Do you understand why it's
inappropriate to use a word like 'love'?"
Mother asked. Jonas nodded. "Yes, thank you, I do," he replied
slowly. It was his first lie to his parents.
[Music]
"Gabriel?" Jonas whispered that night to the new child The crib was in his room again.
After Gabe had slept soundly in Jonas's room for four nights, his parents had
pronounced the experiment a success and Jonas a hero. Gabriel was growing rapidly,
now crawling and giggling across the room and pulling himself up to stand. He
could be upgraded in the Nurturing Center, Father said happily, now that he
slept; he could be officially named and given to his family in December, which
was only 2 months away. But when he was taken away, he stopped sleeping again, and
cried in the night. So he was back in Jonas's sleeping room They would give it
a little more time, they decided. Since Gabe seemed to like it in Jonas's room,
he would sleep there at night a little longer, until the habit of sound sleep was fully
formed. The Nurturers were very optimistic about Gabriel's
future. There was no answer to Jonas's whisper. Gabriel was sound asleep s
Things could change, Gabe," Jonas went on. "Things could be different. I don't
know how there must be some way for things to be different. There could be
colors. "And grandparents," he added, staring through the dimness toward the ceiling
of his sleeping room And everybody would have the memories. "You know about
memories," he whispered, turning toward the crib. Gabriel's breathing was even and
deep. Jonas liked having him there, though he felt guilty about the
secret. Each night he gave memories to Gabriel: memories of boat rides and
picnics in the sun; memories of soft rainfall against window panes memories
of dancing barefoot on a damp lawn gape The new child stirred slightly
in his sleep. Jonas looked over at him. "There could be love J
whispered. The next morning, for the first time, Jonas did not take his
pill. Something within him, something that had grown there through the
memories, told him to throw the pill away
[Music]